Okay, so today's דף daf *daf* is דף זין *daf zayin* and
we're all caught up and we start at the top of זין
עמוד א *zayin amud aleph* at the משנה mishnah *mishna*. Okay, so
we had an interesting משנה Mishnah *mishna* which was
about when a woman remains forbidden to eat תרומה *terumah* but it
was really a sort of a משנה Mishnah, *mishna* about when you
would not go through with the procedure when there were עדים *edim*
in מדינת הים *medinat hayam* when she admitted and so on and
as we'll see that's going to be somewhat of a necessary background
because now we're going to deal with the next steps in the
procedure and now we already know the things that could prevent the
procedure from going forward. So let's take a look here at the
next משנה mishnah. *mishna*. And now we actually begin a nice description
of how the procedure would look. Okay, so this is more descriptive
than it is going to be halakhic, you know, sort of making
halakhic rulings, obviously the implicit sort of הלכה halacha, *halakhah* here, but
it's going to be much more be a descriptive, this משנה Mishna
*mishna* and the big משנה Mishna *mishna* at the bottom of the
דף *daf*. Let's take a look. כיצד עושה לה *Keitzad oso lah*?
How, what would you do with her once it's, once it's, stupid
thing, it's about to, hold on a second, I apologize.
This thing wants to reboot itself on me.
Now people might think you're talking about the woman. It was like
one long sentence.
I don't know what to do. This is going to reboot itself
on me.
You know what, I'm just going to let it reboot and then
I'll restart the video. Okay, so, alright, so, what would
you do, כיצד עושה לה *keitzad oso lah*, what would you do
to her when, you know, when you have to
now see, she was warned and she went into seclusion and now
she has the status of a סוטה Sotah *sotah* and now we
have to go through with the process. So מוליכו לבית דין din,
שבאותו מקום *molicho l'veit din she'be'oto makom*. You bring her to the
בית דין Beis Din *beit din* in that locale. Now again notice,
and this is the point that I've been making from the beginning,
that we have taken something which in the תורה Torah *Torah* is
the husband's sort of jealousy and we have now made it a
judicial matter. We have witnesses and evidence, circumstantial evidence, things that make
us sort of feel that we have to, we the בית דין
Beis Din *beit din*, have to determine what her status is. It's
no longer about the husband. So the first place to bring it,
in the תורה Torah *Torah* of course she's brought to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* directly for the ritual. But here the
first place she's brought is the בית דין Beis Din, *beit din*.
And by doing that, by making that to be, you know, what
do you do in this case, you bring her to a בית
דין Beis Din *beit din*, right? So it makes it that clear
statement that this is about דין din. *din*, right? So that's the
place where she's brought, to a בית דין Beis Din *beit din*.
So you bring her to the local בית דין Beis Din *beit
din*. And what does that בית דין Beis Din *beit din* do?
Now that בית דין Beis Din? *beit din* takes over in terms
of, you know, the supervising the whole procedure. And here's what they
do.
Yes, as I understand you've been trying to say that
what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is trying to do is take it
out of the realm
of the husband's discretion.
Yes, so thank you for pointing that out. I was sort of,
both of those are correct, meaning you're taking something and that happens
a lot, you know, which is that חזל Chazal *Chazal* basically, I
mean we can even just start with the fact that the whole
authority of חזל Chazal *Chazal* and בית דין Beis Din, *beit din*
is based on the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* of על פי התורה אשר
יורוך al pi hatorah asher yorucha. ועל המשפט אשר יאמרו לך תעשה
לא lo, תסור ימין ושמאל *al pi hatorah asher yorucha v'al hamishpat
asher yomru lecha ta'aseh lo tasur yamin u'smol*, which in the תורה
Torah *Torah* is אל הכהנים ואל השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם *el
hakohanim v'el hashofet asher yihiyeh bayamim hahem*. But the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*
are much more dominant or in the plural than the שופט בימים
ההם *shofet bayamim hahem*. But חזל Chazal *Chazal* very often sort of
assert their authority, right, especially if you realize that at the time
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* clearly the authority much
more resided amongst the כהנים *kohanim* than amongst the rabbis. But חזל
Chazal *Chazal* are constantly in describing, you know, those realities asserting their
authority. So for example they speak about a בית דין Beis Din,
*beit din* which would determine, you know, whether a כהן kohen *kohen*
was fit for עבודה *avodah* or not when a question had come
up about his יחוס *yichus* and so on. So you are absolutely
correct that there's also that element. So it's taking something which is
about the husband's passion,
unfounded discretion, and about the בית דין Beis Din *beit din* and
about the כהנים *kohanim* and it's doing two things. It's right, by
putting it into the בית דין Beis Din, *beit din* it's making
it objective sort of based on circumstance, based on testimony and evidence,
and taking it away from the כהנים *kohanim* and ultimately putting it
under the authority of the בית דין beis din *beit din*. So
both of those are correct. So ומוסרו לו שני תלמידי חכמים shnei
talmidei chachamim, *u'mosru lo shnei talmidei chachamim*.
Now by the way, going back to Dose's point, ומוסרו לו שני
תלמידי חכמים shnei talmidei chachamim *u'mosru lo shnei talmidei chachamim* might have
an echo for some people about what happens at ערב יום כיפור
Yom Kippur *erev Yom Kippur* where they have the כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol* is getting ready to learn, you know, to prepare for the
עבודת היום *avodat hayom* and that's a perfect example where if you
read the description in
יומא *Yoma* the בית דין beis din's
*beit din* is overseeing that
whole process and the
בית דין beis din, *beit din* is מוסרו לו *mosru lo*. example
about בית דין beis din being the ones to be חז"ל Chazal
supervise what's going on in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it's
actually exactly that phrase of מוסר לו שני תלמידי חכמים. moser lo
shnei talmidei chachamim. So interestingly you have the same thing here. So
what do they do? They hand over two תורה Torah sages to
the husband, שמא יבוא עליה בדרך, shema yavo aleha baderech, and they
are going to be their escorts and the what's it called the
chaperones, the minders, to accompany them and bring them to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Now by the way for those who are wondering the next stop
in ירושלים Yerushalayim is not ירושלים Yerushalayim בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, any
guess where the next stop is?
ירושלים Yerushalayim to the what else is there? בית דין הגדול Beis
Din Hagadol that's in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash but that's the
next stop. Okay so from one בית דין beis din sending them
to be, you know, sending them off to the Supreme Court. Okay
so it's one בית דין Beis Din, to another בית דין, Beis
Din but the very fact also that there are these two agents
of the בית דין Beis Din that are accompanying them, it says
sort of בית דין Beis Din sort of being part of the
whole plot. At no stage is this now the husband is שלעפינג
shlepping his wife, like the husband is dragging his wife. No, no,
no, we the בית דין Beit Din are sending this case to
be processed and our agents are going along with and we're the
ones essentially bringing her, and we'll see a little bit about that
tension in the גמרא. Gemara. And to the point that it says
שמא יבוא עליה בדרך. shema yavo aleha baderech. We're afraid that, why
are they accompanying? Because maybe he'll have sex with her along the
way. And why would that be a problem? Well because she's a
סוטה Sotah and she's forbidden, husband and wife are forbidden to have
sex once she has the status of a סוטה sotah, until
it's clarified.
And right, we don't just סתם stam we care about everybody's עבירות
aveiros but no, but then the waters won't work, it'll undermine the
whole process, right, because we learn out that it's only when the
man is clean from sin will the waters be effective. So in
order to ensure that this is going to work and be effective,
we have to now supervise. But it makes the man again, notice
what it does, like it really makes the man now an object
of suspicion and he can't now ruin everything, and again, so we
really the בית דין Beit Din are now taking control and making
sure it's going to happen as opposed to being about the man
and his wife, you know the man's initiative and what he wants
to do to his wife. You had a question? סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
yeah, that's why, right, exactly. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר בעלה נאמן עליה.
Rebi Yehuda Omeir baala ne'eman aleha. רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, yes? So
she has to go to
בית דין? Beit Din Yes, went to ירושלים Yerushalayim to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. and in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was the
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, was the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, they had
their what?
They had to go there
anyway to do the water. Well they're going to be going there
anyway but yes, but the way חז"ל Chazal sort of because of
the making it about בית דין, Beit Din you know then everything
is going to first local בית דין, Beit Din from there to
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, and there the בית דין הגדול
Beis Din Hagadol is essentially going to hand it over to the
כהנים for, you know, for the ritual. Now we'll see how central
and necessary the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol is, so we'll
get to that, yes.
So in addition to the חכמים chachamim managing and controlling let's say
the authority of the passions of the husband, right? Because he's jealous
now, he's going to have a fair, he's going to have relations
with her. Would you also say that it's the חכמים's chachamim way
of dealing more rationally with magic the same way of like נחש
nachash like the נחש הנחושת?
nachash hanechoshet?
Well possibly but they don't get away from the fact that there
is going to be a ritual that's going to prove it. But
you're but what you're saying is that by forefronting the בית דין's
Beit Din role, it sort of it backgrounds the ritual and as
we're going to see, they're constantly trying to do things so they
don't have to get to the ritual. So that's a good point
too, it does put in the background the whole focus on this
sort of magical procedure.
And in theory the ritual works but there
could be all kinds of... Right exactly and that's the other thing
that happens, there's so many reasons that the ritual doesn't work that
you know that we heard yesterday that רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon was
afraid that that would undermine the efficacy of the ritual, the reality
is it does undermine the efficacy of the ritual, right, and it's
a way of, you know, possibly explaining why the ritual sometimes wouldn't
work if there's all these other reasons, but it's also a way
I think what Dov
the second Dov said is also a good point, you know it
shifts our focus from the ritual. All of this thing about centralizing
בית דין, Beit Din right, does has all of those types of
effects. Did you have a question? No, okay. All right, so let's
now see the גמרא. Gemara It's really fun this stuff. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, תרי ואיהו דהוו תלתא. trei ve'ihu
dehavu tlata. So we're going to try to figure out why you
needed two representatives of the court. Okay, תרי ואיהו דהוו תלתא, trei
ve'ihu dehavu tlata, so two of the representatives of the chaperones and
the husband, that makes three men there. לימא מסייע ליה לרב, leima
misayei lei le'Rav, let's say this supports רב. Rav. דאמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, לא שנו אלא בעיר, lo
shanu ela be'ir, when do we say that there is a הלכה,
halacha this is now going about... teaching in קידושין Kiddushin that a
משנה Mishna. in קידושין Kiddushin that speaks about an איסור ייחוד, issur
yichud, an איסור issur of a woman being in seclusion with a
man. This is not about the case of the husband warning, this
is just the general איסור issur of ייחוד, yichud, a concern of
a man and a woman shouldn't be in seclusion together if they're
not husband and wife because it might lead to illicit sex, again
married, not married, whatever. So anyway, so the question there is that
it wouldn't be seclusion if there were two men. So let's but
here there's three men. So let's say why do we need three?
Why not just have one תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? So the גמרא
Gemara says maybe this supports what רב Rav says, דאמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, de-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, לא שנו אלא בעיר, lo
shanu ela be-ir,
that when do we say that two men and a woman is
not considered seclusion, again for general laws of ייחוד, yichud, if it's
in a city, אבל בדרך, aval be-derech, if you're going on the
way on a journey, עד דאיכא תלתא, ad de-ika tlasa, you need
three. Why do you need three? שמא יצטרך אחד מהם לנקביו, shema
yitztarech echad me-hem le-nekavav, one person's going to have to go to
the bathroom, okay, and again presumably in the city that would be
a circumstance that would not have to take him away too far,
but here you know but here you know maybe they could have
the other two people wait a few feet away from the bathroom
or something,
there's other people around them
would be less in the city. Well no, no, because we're saying
that these are the only people around, that's how we're measuring whether
it constitutes ייחוד yichud or not. But if you're in the city
you go to some outhouse or wherever you go, I don't know
exactly what setups they had, but anyway but the other two people
are the remaining man and the woman are a few you know
feet away. But if you're out in the middle of nature right
you want to go into the forest a little bit, a little
bit of privacy, so you're going to get a little bit further
away and that's going to leave the two behind in a case
of in a scenario of ייחוד. yichud.
Okay, somebody taking his place.
Oh maybe that's true also, like similar to what Rabbi Dove said,
you could make arrangements that somebody take your place. Maybe that's true
too, you make arrangements somebody take your place. Okay, שמא יצטרך אחד
מהם לנקביו,
shema
yitztarech echad
me-hem le-nekavav, one person has to go to the bathroom, ונמצא אחד
מהם מתייחד עם הערווה, ve-nimtza echad me-hem mityached im ha-erva, and then
the other man is left together with this woman who is a
forbidden, not his wife. So that's so you see that that would
explain why we need two תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because they're going
on a journey and they need to be three men.
It has nothing to do with ערווה erva necessarily, just any
man and any woman who's not ערווה. erva. Right, so the question
is what about פנוי panui and פנויה, pnuya, if she's not a
נדה, niddah, let's not worry about that. We'll do it when we
do קידושין. Kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, הכא היינו
טעמא כי היכי דליהוו עלה סהדי. hacha hainu taama ki heichi de-lehavu
ala sa-hadei. No,
maybe maybe that's true, maybe it's not true, but we can otherwise
explain why you need two. You need two that they should be
witnesses. Now what do they need to be witnesses for? What are
they testifying to? So רש״י Rashi points out that they would testify
to the fact that if he went ahead and had sex with
his wife that they're now going to come and say we cannot
go through with the proceeding, the man had sex with his wife.
Okay, and now you would presumably need a normal evidence you know
normal standard of testimony to prove that. עד אחד ed echad is
believed to say she had sex, it wouldn't be believed she had
sex with a man she was suspected of, not that the husband
and wife had sex on the journey. So so the whole point
is to make sure this doesn't happen and then to treat it
appropriately if it does happen. So you need the two to serve
as
witnesses. So the
גמרא Gemara says, now the
גמרא Gemara has another question: תלמידי חכמים אין כולי עלמא לא? talmidei
chachamim in kuli alma lo? So only Torah sages not others? Now
what's what's that
about? Like if you just need witnesses you know just two people.
Now the
obvious point I think
is that this is to emphasize בית דין Beit Din supervision, בית
דין Beit Din presence. These are like they're not
just סתם stam people learning in a ישיבה, yeshiva, presumably they're learners
of Torah associated with the בית דין, Beit Din, like you know
sort of so they're part of the and therefore that to
emphasize בית דין Beis Din supervision. Maybe okay that's true but
anyway that's what I would say that it emphasizes בית דין Beis
Din, supervision. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. לימא מסייע ליה לאידך דרב, leima mesayei lei le-idach
de-Rav, maybe this supports the
other statement of רב, Rav, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, de-amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, לא שנו. lo shanu. be there learners of תורה
Torah associated with the
בית דין, Beit Din like you know sort of a
so they're part of the and therefore
it's to emphasize. It's not
official then? Maybe. Okay, that's true, but anyway, that's what I would
say, that
it emphasizes בית דין Beit Din supervision. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says: לימא מסייע ליה לאידך דרב, Leima misayei lei l'idach
d'Rav, maybe this supports the other statement of
רב, Rav, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
לא שנו אלא כשרים אבל פרוצים אפילו עשרה נמי לא, lo shanu
ela k'sherim aval prutzim afilu asara nami lo,
that when is it that it's not considered ייחוד yichud when they
are people of sort of of you know upstanding character but if
it's people that are known to be loose with in sexual matters,
and it's interesting who do you put in which category, then even
ten men with a woman can't won't be trusted not to have
sex. מעשה היה והוציאו עשרה במיטה, Maaseh haya v'hotziu asara b'mita, there
was a case actually that they snuck a woman out of a
city on a bed and there were ten men and it was
in order to have sex. I don't know if it means that
all ten were engaged in the sexual act. I hope not, maybe
it does, but anyway, but it only means that that others that
if people are not, you know, are considered פרוץ, parutz, what's the
word? Licentious, or you know, in sexual matters then it doesn't matter
if there are other men around. So the men? The men, the
men. Specifically the men. The idea being that we're not afraid that
this one man and woman will have sex in the presence of
another man. That's why it's not ייחוד. yichud. So it's saying but
if the other man or is somebody that you know is like
has no sexual boundaries, which is sort of the idea of פרוץ,
parutz, then that won't be a restraint. Then they the man will
go and have sex even in the presence of ten other men,
they won't mind if these men are פרוצים. prutzim. So maybe that's
why we need תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and not to I think
to suggest that anybody who's not a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is
a פרוץ, parutz, but this like hopefully ensures that we're not dealing
with פרוצים prutzim and maybe that's what the issue is about. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא הכא היינו טעמא דידעי לאתרויי ביה. Lo
hacha hainu taama d'yadi l'atruyei bei. No, now they'll know to give
him התראה. hatra'ah. So התראה, hatra'ah, now we're back to like classic
דין, din like witnesses and warnings. So why do we need to
give him התראה? hatra'ah? So רש"י Rashi says well, you know, if
a man violates the prohibition or woman of having sex while she's
a סוטה, sotah we're going to learn out that that's a biblical
prohibition and he would be deserving of lashes. So now we want
to send these תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because they'll be know the
הלכה halacha and they'll be able that if he's about to do
it to give him התראה. hatra'ah. Now this is bizarre, right? All
of a sudden we worry that somebody we want to ensure that
somebody's going to get lashes if they deserve it. Like it's one
thing in the context we want to make sure that the סוטה
sotah process continues properly and he that they don't do an act
that's going to interfere with it and that if they do we'll
be able to know about it and interrupt it. But why is
it important for us to make sure that he gets the מלקות
malkos that he deserves? And again, I don't think that I think
ultimately it's probably not so important, but what it does is it
again sort of really says this is about דין. din What's דין
din. about? Witnesses who can give warning, who could make sure you're
going to get lashes if you do it. It sort of it
really forefronts the whole דין din part of the proceeding if we
have witnesses תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim which I think are specifically a
sort of a mini type of a בית דין Beit Din representatives
of the court who can give warning and that again really makes
it all about an ongoing process of דין. din.
And a woman's איסור issur that is מוטל עליו mutal alav now
on the husband.
Yes, but still I'm not sure we would always make want to,
you know, proactively make sure that people are going to get התראה
hatra'ah so they can get punished for the איסור issur that they
do. So again, I just think that bringing התראה hatra'ah to the
forefront is a way of bringing the idea of דין din, to
the forefront.
Yes. What about making sure we have the clear that he violated
לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and then we can't go through the proceeding,
like even if he didn't he didn't have warning, we still wouldn't
go through if we knew he had sex.
No, I mean it would not matter whether he got warning or
not, the violation would be enough to not go through. So the
only purpose of התראה? hatra'ah?
Is just so that then it wouldn't be a full.
No, no, it would be biblical. It's just that a biblical violation
without the without warning isn't deserving of lashes, but that would be
the only difference. Is it דוב? Dov? Did you want to? Okay.
All right. So now we'll continue, finally getting the video here started.
Okay, so continuing here on ז עמוד א, Zayin Amud Aleph, we
pick up at the two dots. Oh, so we just mentioned that
you need the two as not just to prevent to get out
of a normal ייחוד yichud situation, but also to serve as witnesses
and to be able the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to serve as
warning, again asserting בית דין Beit Din, sort of supervision over the
whole process and presence in the whole process. Take a look also
תוספות, Tosafos, interesting תוספות Tosafos I wanted to mention. תוספות Tosafos says
כי היכי דידעי לאתרויי ביה, Ki heichi d'yadi l'atruyei bei, תוספות Tosafos
says והכי אמרינן נמי בפרק אלו הן הגולין גבי גולין לעיר מקלט
ומושיבין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יהרגנו בדרך. v'hachi amrinan nami b'perek
elu hen hagolin gabi golin l'ir miklat u'moshivin lo shnei talmidei chachamim
shema yeihargenu baderech. Okay,
so when you send somebody to an עיר מקלט ir miklat who
killed by accident,
he's accompanied with two תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim lest the גואל הדם
goel hadam attacks this guy בדרך. baderech. Now notice of this really
interesting comparison, because the first day we were learning סוטה sotah, I
pointed out that you have these two cases in the תורה Torah
where a start as vigilante justice or taking the law into your
own hands type of a thing and חז"ל Chazal and the תורה
Torah work to bring it under some form of control. So the
biggest example of of the cases of the תורה Torah, doing it
is about the גואל הדם goel hadam with the accidental murder, right?
And the תורה Torah. actually does what the תורה Torah does to
that is what חז"ל Chazal are doing to the סוטה, Sotah, right?
It says ושלחו זקני עירו ולקחו אותו משם, v'shalchu ziknei iro v'lakchu
oto misham, you know, that they send him to the עיר מקלט,
ir miklat, they retrieve... even from the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat עד
עמדו ad omdo לפני העדה למשפט. lifnei ha-edah l'mishpat. לפני העדה למשפט.
lifnei ha-edah l'mishpat.
No, no, no, this is not going to be vigilante justice, the
בית דין Beit Din. is going to take control, they're going to
control the whole proceedings and so on, right? So סוטה, Sotah. I
think some of you mentioned, maybe there was the first step in
that in the תורה, Torah. that it took it out of honor
killings and made it about a procedure in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash And then חזל Chazal take it to the next step to
make it about דין. din But notice here the similar parallel, that
by the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, you make sure that the person
is accompanied with שני תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim? right? So again, the
בית דין's Beit Din presence throughout the whole process by the ערי
מקלט Arei Miklat and their presence throughout the whole process here by
סוטה. Sotah And תוספות Tosafot points out there the גמרא Gemara says
why two תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim ודקה הגמרא מאי לאו דאסרו בי
די קטלו בר קטלהו? v'dakah ha-Gemara mai lav d'asru bei di katlu
bar katlahu? The two תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim. are necessary so if
the גואל הדם Goel HaDam is about to kill this guy, they'll
be able to kill the גואל הדם. Goel HaDam. Okay, again to
give התראה. hatra'ah. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמא גבי התראה בעינן
תלמידי חכמים. alma gabei hatra'ah ba'inan talmidei chachamim. So תוספות Tosafot says
well, based on the way the גמרא Gemara explains both of those
cases being about התראה, hatra'ah, you need תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim, Now,
I don't know, we've never heard before you דווקא davka need תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim it might say that תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim ensure
that they know what to do, but it doesn't mean that a
התראה hatra'ah by a non-תלמיד חכם talmid chacham wouldn't count. But what
I really wanted to show you was how stark the parallel here
is between these two cases about the בית דין Beit Din ensuring
that it's about a בית דין Beit Din type of a procedure,
yes.
Are there also two cases that parallel in terms of the situations
of death or?
Right, that's a very good point. And that element of passion and
us sort of calming everything down and right, exactly, right. So all
these things are there, right, taking it away from sort of the
passionate individual vigilante, making it judicial, calming everybody down, making our presence,
and as we said before, taking it out of being like בית
דין Beit Din, asserting that even a מקדש Mikdash type of a
ritual, ultimately it's about חזל and the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim. and
בית דין Beit Din are the ones that ultimately are the central
to it and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, is under their authority,
which also we've seen as I mentioned by the שני תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim by the like by עבודת יום הכפורים. Avodas Yom Kippurim.
It's so funny there, the whole thing
is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. ritual, it's all about the centrality
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and the way the גמרא Gemara
describes, the משנה Mishnah, describes, right, the עבודת יום הכפורים, Avodas Yom
Kippurim, this בית דין Beit Din is overseeing the whole process.
All right. The point I think is really powerful is according to
the framework you're laying out, this whole thing is חזל's attempt to
impose a rational control over sort of crimes of passion, revenge, adultery,
vengeance, and jealousy.
Yeah, I think it's a great, great point. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי יהודה אומר בעלה נאמן עליה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer ba'alah ne'eman aleha. The husband is believed, which means that
you don't need the two תלמידי חכמים. We trust that he will
not have sex with her. Okay, but that again, if it's not
just we'll trust not have sex, it changes the dynamics a lot.
It means that during, what's the experience when they're leaving their town
and going to ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Is the experience בית דין Beit Din
is now bringing this woman to judgment or is the experience the
husband, the jealous husband is now bringing his wife? Right, so I
think it makes a huge difference whether you have the presence of
the two תלמידי חכמים there. So let's see what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says. תניא ותנא ברייתא Tanya u'tana beraisa רבי יהודה אומר בעלה
נאמן מקל וחומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer ba'ala ne'eman mi'kal v'chomer.
We can trust the husband not to have sex with her from
a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? ומה
נדה שהיא בכרת בעלה נאמן עליה. u'mah niddah she'hi b'kares ba'ala ne'eman
aleha. A נדה niddah
which is, the punishment is כרת, kares, a very weighty transgression, we
trust the husband and wife to sleep together in the same room
and not to have sex. So סוטה שהיא בלאו, Sotah she'hi b'lav,
a סוטה Sotah which is a simple negative prohibition of husband and
wife having sex when she's in this suspected state, so which we'll
learn it out later where that's from, לא כל שכן? lo kol
sheken? How much more so can we trust him to be not
to transgress?
רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis would say,
היא הנותנת, hi hanosanes, no, that argument that you said is exactly
the argument why we don't trust him. נדה דכרת חמירא ליה ומהימן,
niddah d'kares chamira lei u'meheiman, נדה's niddah very weighty, it's כרת, kares,
he's going to, he'll be careful about that, we can trust him.
סוטה בלאו לא חמירא ליה ולא מהימן, Sotah b'lav lo chamira lei
v'lo meheiman, סוטה sotah. which is a simple negative prohibition, it's not
so weighty and we won't trust him to keep to it. רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי
יהודה מקל וחומר מייתי לה? Rabbi Yehuda mi'kal v'chomer mayisay lah? Does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda want to back his argument from a קל
וחומר? kal v'chomer? והא רבי יהודה מקראי מייתי לה. v'ha Rabbi Yehuda
mi'kray mayisay lah. He brings it from a פסוק. pasuk. דתניא ותנא
ברייתא: de'tanya u'tana beraisa: והביא האיש את אשתו אל הכהן. v'heivi ha'ish
es ishto el hakohein. The man shall bring the wife. And again,
notice, right, this is how is the process conceived? Is it the
man bringing the wife or בית דין Beit Din bringing her? So
והביא האיש את אשתו אל הכהן. v'heivi ha'ish es ishto el hakohein.
מן התורה איש מביא את אשתו. min haTorah ish meivi es ishto.
Biblically, the man brings the wife. אבל אמרו חכמים, aval amru chachamim,
but the sages said, מוסרין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יבוא עליה
בדרך. mosrin lo shnei talmidei chachamim shema yavo aleha baderech. No, we
have to have these sages in order lest he, lest he have
sex. That's position number one, which sounds like our משנה, Mishnah but
again, it also shows the contrast of how this is a, becomes
a different process from the one in the תורה. Torah רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says: בעלה נאמן עליה
מקל וחומר. ba'ala ne'eman aleha mi'kal v'chomer. So
what... What we had in the ברייתא braita was Rabbi Yehuda's קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, in this ברייתא braita is Rabbi Yosei's קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Okay? No, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה נדה
שהיא בכרת בעלה נאמן עליה סוטה שהיא בלאו לא כל שכן? u'mah
niddah shehi b'karet ba'ala ne'eman aleiha sotah shehi b'lav lo kol sheken?
If he can be trusted by נדה, niddah, how much more so
should he be trusted by סוטה. sotah, אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said back to, now it's Rabbi Yosei, לא, no. אם אמרת בנדה
שיש לה היתר. im amarta b'niddah she'yesh la heter. By
a נדה niddah he can be trusted because after she goes to
the מקוה, mikveh, you know, she'll be permissible to him again. It's
so, you know, it's a regular type of a cycle there. But
תאמר בסוטה שאין לה היתר? tomar b'sotah she'ein la heter? By the
סוטה, sotah, if it turns out that she's guilty, there's no, you
know, there's she'll never be permitted. So maybe he figures this is
his last chance. Okay, so number one, that
that even besides the fact that they said before that because it's
not as weighty, he'll be more ready to transgress, but because also
he, you know, it's maybe more permanent, he'll be more ready to
transgress. ואומר, ve'omer, and in addition there's another thing going on here:
מים גנובים ימתקו, mayim genuvim yimtaku, stolen waters are sweet. Now, תוספות
Tosafot asks, why did you need this second one? So תוספות Tosafot
says because maybe you'll say, look, he's had sex with her before,
how could you say it's such a sense of urgency? No, now
that she's forbidden, maybe that even makes it a little bit more,
you know, more attractive,
more of a seduction, so to, of a temptation, I should
say. So tempted. Anyway, so that's how they pushed back and said
why it is important. So now we have Rabbi Yosei arguing the
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, and let's see what Rabbi Yehuda says. Rabbi
Yehuda in the first ברייתא braita was the קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
let's see what he says here. רבי יהודה אומר מן התורה יביא
את אשתו לכהן, Rabbi Yehuda omer min haTorah yavi et ishto l'kohen,
no, from the תורה Torah the man does it, שנאמר והביא האיש
את אשתו. shenemar v'hevi ha'ish et ishto.
So, and now he says, no, look, it's enough for the man
to bring it, end of story, it's in the תורה. Torah So
what about the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? In the first ברייתא braita
he had a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, here he just quotes the
פסוק. pasuk So the גמרא Gemara says, מעיקרא אמר להו קל וחומר
ברישא. me'ikara amar lehu kal vachomer b'reisha. No, first he argued the
קל וחומר kal vachomer like Rabbi Yosei did. ופרכוה, u'parchuha, and then
they pushed back and they showed it wasn't a good קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. והדר אמר להו קרא, ve'hadar amar lehu kra, so then
he said, fine, forget the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but let's just
go back to the פסוקים, psukim, it's the man, it's not the
בית דין, Beit Din end of story. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, רבי יהודה היינו תנא קמא. Rabbi Yehuda haynu Tanna Kamma.
Wait a minute, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma also conceded that from
the תורה's Torah, perspective, it's the man. So how are they different?
They're all admitting that from the תורה's Torah perspective it's the man.
So the גמרא Gemara says the obvious difference, which is a little
difference which is a big difference, איכא בינייהו אבל אמרו. ika beinaihu
aval amru. No, the difference is is whether חז"ל did something to
change it. Okay? Everybody concedes from the תורה's Torah, perspective it's the
man bringing his wife. The question is, did the rabbis say, yes,
that's from the תורה, Torah but we're going to now go out
and do something to change it. And Rabbi Yehuda says, I don't
want you to change the procedure. Okay? Now what's very interesting is
the way the גמרא Gemara. frames it is that Rabbi Yehuda concedes
that maybe there is some basis to be afraid they'll have sex.
But nevertheless, let's not mess with it the way the תורה's described
it, which might push that, you know, Rabbi Yehuda's trying to say,
I don't want to change the nature of the whole process to
the degree that you're changing it. I want to keep it a
little closer to its biblical origins, you know, with the husband sort
of, you know, being the one to be the sort of initiator
or the one who's really the driver of the whole thing. Right?
Now it's interesting to ask, let me just check quickly
here. No, okay, fine. So, so let's see now the next משנה.
Mishnah But that becomes again, I think that really does change the
nature of how the process is, the whole dynamic of the process.
Is isn't there a reason why you need these two people alone
for that length of time?
Like, well, Rabbi Yehuda says we can leave them alone.
No, like, sorry, not in the sense of having, not in the
sense of them deciding to have sex, but of hurting each
other or running away because they really don't want to go do.
Oh, that's an interesting question. Maybe because he's, oh, that's an interesting
question, like why aren't we afraid? That's a really good point because
if the woman is sort of in a position of a like
of a suspect, right, so why are we not afraid that they'll,
that she'll try to escape? She would never escape. Right, right, right.
Or how about the possibility
they may want to make up? Like did she, does he?
Oh, but that's okay. No, that's okay. No, well, it's not okay
once she's a סוטה, sotah. making up won't work because they can't
have sex again because he, before it declares her a סוטה.
sotah, Like someone should have educated him to the ramifications of the
whole process.
Right.
Calm down now. Now he's over the passion.
Right, they're going together.
Now look what he got.
Yeah, well, I think that's part of
this thing, they saying what did we do? Right.
Well, that's in a way if you remember going back to the
first דף of the גמרא. Gemara The question was like אסור לקנאות.
assur l'kanot. The opinion of אסור לקנאות assur l'kanot one of the
reasons of אסור מן בזמן הזה assur min bazman hazeh was you'll
get yourself stuck and then you can't, you know, retract. I have
to tell you, by the way, not exactly this but very similarly,
these types of things happen today. I mean, I know of a
case, a man suspected his wife of committing adultery, so what did
he do? He went ahead and he hired a private eye and
he got all of this evidence, you know, photographs and the whole
thing. And then they wanted to make up, but then there's a
big problem according to הלכה halacha because if. That amount of evidence,
right, and forget suspected adultery, that was known adultery, right? How do
you, how do you get, if it's just a woman who's admitting
to her husband, there's tricks you can talk about that you technically
have to believe her, but you know, sometimes you get yourself into
a real bind. So it's absolute correct. Now by saying that he
had to have witnesses at the stage of the warning, right, so
hopefully that formalizes the process of warning, which means that he'll take
a moment to pause before it. And remember in the משנה Mishnah
while the גמרא Gemara, quoted a ברייתא Baraita of an opinion that
you didn't need witnesses for the warning, in the משנה both opinions
required witnesses for the warning. So hopefully at that stage by formalizing
that process it'll be a moment of pause, but you're right, he
can get himself totally stuck. But your point is also a really
good one, right, you know, because at some degree he's not yet
a fully suspected person, you know, I guess it's a good question
in general, right, what happens, you know, with somebody who suspected of
in the middle of a court proceeding, of like do we have
a discussion of somebody essentially like being in jail? You know, let's
take a simple case, right, witnesses come and say ראובן Reuven killed
שמעון, Shimon, and you know, you're going through the whole court case,
is there an assumption, like what do you do with him during
the process of a court? Yeah, it's a good point.
Okay, so let's take a look at the next משנה. היו מעלין
אותה לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים. Hayu maalin osah le-Beis Din Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim.
They would bring her to the, now so go from one בית
דין Beit Din to the next בית דין, Beit Din right, not
straight to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now it's true that the
בית דין הגדול שבירושלים Beis Din Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim was in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash but that's not the focus. Okay, ומאיימין עליה, u-me-ayemin
aleha,
and they scare her, כדרך שמאיימין על עדי נפשות, ke-derech she-me-ayemin al
edei nefashot, like
they would scare people to come to testify about, what do you
call it, about capital crimes. So what they do is somebody's coming
to testify in capital crimes, they really want to make sure they're
not lying. So first they scare the wits out of them, like
in case you know, if you think, if you're not totally certain
what you say, maybe you're filling in some gaps, you know, you're
a little bit estimating or whatever, you should know you know that
if this person dies on account of your testimony which isn't totally
true, his you know basically you'll be, you'll have spilled his blood,
you'll be responsible for future generations, like they scare the wits out
of them. And then what they do though is they say on
the other hand, if you really do know what you're doing and
you don't testify, it'll also be a terrible thing. So basically like
you know trying to make sure that if they can, if they
are going to be you know good witnesses they will testify, but
if there's a little bit of a question that they won't testify.
So they sort of scare them both ways. So here they're going
to scare her. So again notice the emphasis of how much we're
making it like דין, din. right, like we scare there we scare
here, you know. It's a different type of a purpose of the
scaring, but again all of these parallels are explicitly being drawn. So
let's take a look.
Okay, מעלין אותה לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים ומאיימין עליה, Maalin osah le-Beis
Din Hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim u-me-ayemin aleha, you scare her, כדרך שמאיימין על עדי
נפשות, ke-derech she-me-ayemin al edei nefashot, ואומר לה, ve-omer lah, you say
to her, or ואומרים לה. ve-omrim lah. בתי, Biti, my daughter, הרבה
יין עושה, harbeh yayin osah, you know
wine often has a big effect, meaning like basically they're trying to
get her to admit, but we know it's hard to admit that
you like you know you willingly did such a you know terrible
sin or betrayal of your spouse or whatever, so we're giving her
extenuating
circumstances. Like you know say, look, sometimes people sin, they drink too
much, they do things they regret in the morning or whatever, like
so making it possible for her to say yes she did it,
but not you know not feel the full weight of the responsibility
in coming across with the admission. You know sometimes wine causes a
lot of people to act in ways they wouldn't have acted, הרבה
יין עושה, harbeh yayin osah, or you know being too frivolous, הרבה
שחוק עושה, harbeh se-chok osah, הרבה ילדות עושה, harbeh yaldus osah, if
you're young and you know maybe your passions get control of you,
or you're not you know, הרבה שכנים רעים עושים, harbeh shechenim raim
osim, sometimes we're egged on by our you know by our bad
company and our
neighbors and you know they incite us to do things. עשי לשמו
הגדול, asi lishmo hagadol, now basically do the right thing, do for
the name of God's great, of God's great name, שנכתב בקדושה, she-nichtav
bi-kedushah, that would be written in holiness, שלא ימחה על המים, she-lo
yimachei al hamayim, that it should not be scraped into the water.
So it's interesting that the focus here is why do we want
her to admit? Right, you know why you want to get a
normal person you suspect of committing a crime to admit is it
saves you the cost of the trial and it saves you the
possibility that you know you're going to lose. Right, I mean that's
why the prosecution tries to get somebody you know to just you
know to plead guilty and they'll make a plea bargain or whatever.
Although whatever, it's terrible, I'm not going to enter that, there's been
a lot written about how they get so many innocent people to
plead guilty because of the whole way the system is you know
is biased against you once you're caught up in that system. But
anyway, so but here like what's the benefit? If we trust that
the ritual, the water is going to work, why are we trying
to get her to admit? Now you could talk about, well, you
know, it's better at least for somebody's own you know sense that
they own up on themselves as if they're found guilty just you
know from a human perspective, you know that, or you could say,
well I don't know maybe the other things we said, the water
doesn't always work, maybe we don't want her to die, you know,
but it's interesting here that the focus is totally on, we don't
want to have
to So שלא ימחה
על המים shelo yimacheh al hamayim that it should not be dissolved
in the water. ואומר לפניה דברים שאינם כדאי לשומען ve'omer lefaneha devarim
she'einam kedai leshom'an
and they say to her things that are not fit to
be heard, היא וכל שאינה כדאי לשומען, hi vechol she'eina kedai leshom'an,
היא וכל משפחת בית אביה, hi vechol mishpachat beit aviha, she and
her entire family. So what are those things that are not fit
for being heard? We'll see in the Gemara. אם אמרה טמאה אני
im amrah tme'ah ani but they scare the wits out of her.
If she says I am טמאה, tme'ah, שוברת כתובתה shoveret ktuvatah she
writes a receipt for her כתובה, ktuvah, not that she got the
payment, she loses her כתובה, ktuvah, okay? ויוצאה veyotzah and she gets
divorced. She admitted, she's divorced, doesn't get her כתובה, ktuvah, end of
story. ואם אמרה טהורה אני ve'im amrah tehorah ani if she says
she is טהורה, tehorah, no I'm innocent, מעלין אותה לשער המזרח ma'alin
otah leshaar hamizrach
you bring her to the eastern gate of the מקדש Mikdash which
is opposite שער ניקנור, shaar nikanor, right? Basically the way the מקדש
Mikdash is, if you think about it, right, if this is like
the whole thing, if this is the east, right, so this you
walk in and this is the עזרת נשים. ezrat nashim. So this
is like the eastern gate when you get into the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. And then like midway here at the end of the
עזרת נשים, ezrat nashim, you have some steps up and you have
the עזרה azarah where they are actually the מזבח mizbe'ach is or
whatever, and the עזרת ישראל. ezrat yisrael. And at the top of
those steps you have the שער ניקנור, shaar nikanor, the Nicanor gate,
which is leading from the עזרת נשים ezrat nashim top of the
steps into the actual עזרה. azarah. Okay? So it says by the
סוטה, sotah it says that she is presented לפני ה' lifnei Hashem
before God, which ultimately is going to mean standing in the Nicanor
gate which is opposite, you know, the in the time of the
Torah it would have been the אהל מועד, ohel moed, now it
would be in the היכל, heichal,
okay, and the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so you bring her to the
eastern gate which is opposite the שער ניקנור, shaar nikanor, שעל פתח
שער ניקנור, she'al petach shaar nikanor, ששם משקין את הסוטות. shesham mashkin
et hasotot.
Now in the שער ניקנור, shaar nikanor, there they cause the סוטות
sotot to drink, ומטהרין את היולדות umetaharin et hayoldot and you purify
the women who have given birth, ומטהרין את המצורעים umetaharin et hametzora'im
and you purify those that are the lepers. What does that mean?
The gate of Nicanor is the width of the gate, I don't
know if anybody has ever been through sometimes these city gates, you
know, these ancient city gates, it's like you could have like three
feet of stone, you know what I'm saying? Like it's really, really
big. So שער ניקנור shaar nikanor was
like a gate in a wall, so there was a thickness. So
that area, that thickness in that gate was actually did not have
קדושת עזרה. kedushat azarah. It had the קדושה kedusha of עזרת נשים,
ezrat nashim, which was not the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה. azarah.
So therefore that allowed people that were not totally טהור tahor to
come and stand there while the procedure that would finish to purify
them was done. So for example a woman who had given birth
who needed a קרבן. korban. Now in theory she could have sent
somebody to bring it, but this allowed her to be there in
that gate as her קרבן korban was being brought, because she couldn't
enter into the עזרה azarah itself, but she could be standing in
that gate. It allowed a מצורע metzora who was not able to
yet go into the עזרה azarah and here you needed him there
because you needed to put the blood of the קרבן korban on
his thumbs. Well how could you do that if he couldn't stand
in the עזרה? azarah? So he stood in the thickness of that
wall, of that gate, and he put his thumbs out and they
put the blood on his thumbs while he was standing in the
thickness of the wall. That's actually a whole halakhic question whether ביאה
במקצת שמה ביאה bi'ah b'miktzat shemah bi'ah whether partial entry into the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? when you're טמא tamei is considered like an
entry or not, because his thumbs went in. Anyway, so here also
is where the סוטה sotah would stand. Now what's quite fascinating I
should say about this comparison is that and
his right toe,
I guess same way, stuck out yes, stuck out his foot.
So okay, just not both at the same time, that's all. That's
right.
So the interesting thing here about the comparison, we've been comparing this
to a judicial case, but now it's being compared to a different
case, to a טומאה וטהרה tum'ah v'taharah case. And notice the phrase
טמאה אני, tme'ah ani, טהורה אני. tehorah ani. Now that's echoing the
Torah's language, right, ונטמאה, venitme'ah, and היא לא נטמאה. hi lo nitme'ah.
But it's very different. This is not a purification process. This doesn't
make her pure. I mean, it sort of proves she's innocent, which
is like making her pure, but she halakhically is allowed to enter
into the בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash, She doesn't have a טומאה tum'ah
that means she can't enter into the עזרה. azarah. She's not like
a יולדת yoledet and a מצורע. metzora. טומאה? tum'ah? You mean defiled
because of having committed adultery. So it becomes very interesting that we're
also now trying to put it in a טומאה tum'ah category, right?
And talk about the fact that seeing her situated where other טמאים
tme'im are situated. And again, maybe this is and this gets to
this question before, maybe this is to try to deal with this
sort of magic of the סוטה Sotah water. So before it was
said maybe a way we deal with it is we emphasize the
דין din and we background the whole focus on that process which
maybe maybe will come at the end if we don't succeed in
stopping it at any time. earlier. But what this also maybe does
is allows us to reframe it as a טהרה tahara process. You
know, טהרה tahara processes, we know there are weird טהרה tahara processes,
there's one where you send birds off and you dip them in
blood, right? There's ones
where you put the blood on the fingers. So here's a process
she brings a מנחה mincha and you write some words on a
parchment and you have her drink it, right? If you think of
it as a טהרה tahara process, not as a, not as some
like trial by ordeal, it also situates it, situates it in a
place which is more understandable and something more recognizable. So it's very
interesting here that we are now making this explicit comparison to these
other טמאים. tmei-im.
Okay, I'm trying to remember though standard practice women did not generally
enter into the עזרה? azara?
Yes,
it is true that there's a question like whether women are allowed
in the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, whether they needed special reason to
or just as a general practice they weren't or whatever, but again,
that would not be because, so, maybe, maybe, but it doesn't sound
like in general we don't have a problem, if a woman needs
to be in the עזרה azara she would be in the עזרה.
azara.
So it does sound like the comparison is going further than that.
It's not like, oh, there was a problem she's a woman, we
didn't want her in.
Yeah, but is there a question about where she's standing, if a
foot goes into the?
Yeah, it would be the same as the thumb, yeah. Okay.
Okay. הכהן אוחז בבגדיה. Hacohen ochez bivgadeha. Now the Cohen grabs onto
her garments. אם נקרעו נקרעו, im nikre'u nikre'u, ואם נפרמו נפרמו. ve-im
nifremu nifremu.
If they were rended, they were rended. If they were torn in
half, like נפרם nifram is like not just, not just sort of
torn a little bit, but like ripped, like totally like a very
big severing into two pieces. Okay, he would tear her garments and
no matter how much they, they tore, or hold onto her garments
even if they tore. וכהן אוחז, ve-cohen ochez, okay, עד שהוא מגלה
לבה, ad she-hu megaleh libba, until he basically would expose her heart,
literally expose her chest. So we'll see about that in a minute.
So it's interesting because here it sounds like if by accident it
tore, but now it sounds like explicitly he's tearing her garments. Why
else is he holding it if not to tear it? וסותר את
שערה. ve-soter et se'arah. And he would undo her hair, he would
expose her hair, which is right in the Torah. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, אם היה לבה נאה, im haya libba na'eh, if
her heart, but literally like her bosom was, was attractive, לא היה
מגלהו. lo haya megalehu. He would not expose her, okay, because this
is an interesting question, right? This is all done to sort of
to degrade her, but in the process you're, you're uncovering things that
are normally covered. And how much is this also becoming an erotic
experience for the people that are around, right? So that becomes a
whole tension going on here. ואם היה שערה נאה, ve-im haya se'arah
na'eh, and if her hair was beautiful, לא היה סותרו. lo haya
sotro. He would not undo it. היתה מתכסה בלבנים, hayta mitkasa be-levanim,
if she had been wearing white garments, מכסה בשחורים. mekasa bi-shchorim. You'd
dress her in black garments. I don't know where they would do
this change of clothes. Before they got to the בית המקדש? Beit
ha-Mikdash Presumably not after he ripped her garment, presumably before you'd do
the ripping, she was wearing these more unpleasant clothes. It's not exactly
clear at what stage here they're doing this. היה לה כלי זהב,
haya lah klei zahav, if she was wearing nice golden jewelry,
וקטליות ve-katliot and various types, ונזמים וטבעות, ve-nezamim ve-tabbaot, various rings and
chokers and whatever, earrings, מעבירין ממנה, ma'avirin mimena, you remove them from
her, כדי לנוולה, kedei lenavla, in order to dishevel her, in order
to make her
look repulsive. Okay, now the interesting thing is here it seems like
it wasn't just that she comes in with outfits, that there's actually
a process of degrading her by stripping her of these things, right?
That sort of seems to be very much the process. ואחר כך
מביא חבל מצרי, ve-achar kach mevi chevel mitzri, and then afterwards you
would take this type of a, of Egyptian rope, a certain type
of a rope, וקושרו למעלה מדדיה, ve-koshro le-mala mi-dadeha, and you would
bind it above her breasts, to hold up the garment so it
would not continue to fall down, which is funny, like, that probably
was after they got ripped. So probably this whole thing about wearing
the black clothes and taking off the jewelry was probably before, right?
Or else there's a little bit of a gap of time there.
So probably first you would do the black clothes and take off
the jewelry, then he'd rip the garments and then afterwards tie them
up again so they wouldn't fall down. וכל הרוצה לראות בא לראות.
ve-chol ha-rotze lir'ot ba lir'ot. And now it's making a public spectacle
of it, which is not in the Torah. The Torah does not
have it as a public spectacle. This makes a public spectacle of
it. And that's also interesting to talk, think about, because is this
particularly doing something different, right? And this very much fits into issues
we were just discussing. It had goes from a private enterprise between
a husband and a jealous husband and his wife to a type
of a דין. din? Well, דין din is something in which is
done in front of the public and we actually know, what do
we know about דין? din We know that there's some cases the
Torah explicitly says, what does the Torah say? It says וכל העם
ישמעו ויראו. ve-chol ha-am yishme'u ve-yira'u. Sometimes some of the purpose of
punishment is to serve as a public warning and so
maybe so is partly this shift that might have a lot had
to do with the shift again from this private thing between husband
and wife to then we are now turning it into a public
spectacle. It is though interesting to think about two other points about
this, making it a public spectacle. One is what's his name, somebody,
I can't remember, some biblical scholar recently, or not so recent, anyway,
you know, writes a lot about how חז"ל turn a lot of
things that go on in המקדש, ha-Mikdash, they make them more public.
Specifically, for example, if you think, we mentioned יום כיפור before, but
he does talk about the other חגים chagim as well, which are
things which are like, you know, וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד
בבואו לכפר בקודש, V'chol adam lo yihyeh b'Ohel Mo'ed b'vo'o l'chaper bakodesh,
like just totally him and God going in and so on. And
we have like everybody is gathered there to hear the reading of
the תורה, to see the red string turn white, to see him
select for the goat, right, we've turned it into a public sort
of ritual. So on the one hand, this also fits that pattern.
It's in בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. but we're bringing the public into
it and making it a public ritual. The other thing that's interesting
and that I forgot to mention before is a very important insight
by ישי רוזן-צבי Yishai Rosen-Zvi who wrote a book on מסכת סוטה
Masechet Sotah called הטקס שלא היה, Ha-tekes she-lo hayah, the ritual that
never happened. And he says that if you look at the משנה,
and we will see more of this in the גמרא, Gemara the
משנה assumes from the very beginning that she's guilty. And the whole
purpose from the משנה for this ritual is basically not to clarify
if she's innocent or guilty, but to punish her. The purpose of
the סוטה Sota water is that she gets her due punishment. Okay,
so he says the משנה never suggests what happens if she's innocent.
What happens if it works out that she did not commit it?
So, and he says think about the way we scared her beforehand.
What did we say when we scared her? We said,
you know, please, we understand why you might have sinned, just admit
it, don't make us have to erase the name. We never say,
oh, but if you actually are innocent, then you should go through
with it so you can be back with your husband, right? When
we scare the witnesses, we scare them in both directions. Here we
only scare her in one direction. We're assuming that she's guilty. So
if you assume that she's guilty, you understand why you want to
make this a public ritual, right? Why you want to make this
a public spectacle. Because if it's just a court case to clarify,
everybody else doesn't have to be around. But if we know what's
going to happen, right, think about when they had the public hangings,
right, that would be like the entertainment of the month. We know
what's going to happen, so A to, you know, for a punishment
for her everybody should be gathered, and you know, for the lesson
for the עם. am. So again, if the presumption of her guilt
also is what makes this a public spectacle.
What? Okay, right. Or you could say maybe it's all of this
is just
that you want her to admit. That's true too.
But it just diminishes your overarching point, right? How? Because it's mitigating
the integrity of a judicial process by assuming that she's guilty.
Yeah, and then why are we doing it?
Makes it more
terrible.
Well, because of the קינוי kinui and the סתירה. stirah. But I
know, but so what, right? Look, we'll quote, the גמרא Gemara is
going to quote the תוספתא Tosefta and other, there are other תנאיתי
Tannaitic opinions that are constantly saying, wait, she might be innocent, why
are we all making, why are we taking this? But yeah, it's
a good point. I mean, you're right, it does sort of make
it less about דין din and more directly just about judgment, about
punishment rather than about adjudication. Right, that's true. Okay, so that was
his insight, ישי רוזן-צבי. Yishai Rosen-Zvi. But again, what is worth noting
is we took something that is a private thing between husband and
wife in בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, and we've turned this into this
public spectacle, okay, which very much does fit the idea כל העם
ישמעו ויראו kol ha-am yishme'u v'yira'u and the דין din idea and
so on and the punishment idea. וכל הרוצה לראות בא ורואה, V'chol
harotzeh lir'ot ba v'roeh, anybody who wants to see, come and see.
חוץ מעבדיה ושפחותיה, chutz me-avadeha u-shifchoteha, we don't allow her servants to
be there. מפני שלבה גס בהן, mipnei she-libbah gas bahen, because that
sort of bolsters her sense of confidence, her servants are there, A
she maybe doesn't want to admit because her servants are there, B
it makes her feel, oh, you know, I'm still an important person,
I've got my servants, so it will make her not want to,
you know, be cowed by the proceedings.
וכל הנשים מותרות לראותה, v'chol ha-nashim mutarot lir'otah, and all the women
can come and see her. So the גמרא Gemara, says we just
said everybody could come and see her. But okay, we'll talk about
that in the גמרא, Gemara, all the women should come and see
her, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, ונוסרו כל הנשים ולא תעשינה כזמתכנה, v'nossru kol ha-nashim
v'lo taasena k'zimatchena, and all the women will take מוסר, mussar, will
take heed, and will not do like her fornication. Okay, so this
is a פסוק in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, not exactly about this, but whatever,
and so, so again, it's like a, it's almost saying כל העם
ישמעו ויראו, kol ha-am yishme'u v'yira'u, right, turns it into that דין
of כל העם ישמעו ויראו. kol ha-am yishme'u v'yira'u. Let's take a
look at the גמרא, try to get a little bit further. מנא
הני מילי, Mena hani millei, where do you know this from? So
אמר רבי חייא בר גמדא אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Chiyya bar Gamda amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, how do you know
that you bring her to the בית דין הגדול, Beit Din ha-Gadol,
which is again
asserting בית דין's oversight and really sort of running the whole show?
אתיה תורה תורה, atya Torah Torah, כתיב הכא ועשה לה הכהן את
כל התורה הזאת, ketiv hacha v'asah lah ha-kohen et kol ha-Torah ha-zot,
the כהן shall do all of this teaching, all of this ritual.
and וכתיב התם Uch'siv hasom על פי התורה al pi hatorah, אשר
יורוך. It says by the זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, by the תורה
that they teach that they teach you you should do. מה להלן
בשבעים ואחד, Ma lehalan b'shivim v'echad, the same way the זקן ממרא
Zaken Mamre is only if he rebels against the סנהדרין הגדול, Sanhedrin
HaGadol, אף כאן בשבעים ואחד, af kan b'shivim v'echad, here too על
פי התורה, על התורה הזאת al hatorah hazos means that it's ultimately
overseen by the בית דין הגדול. Beit Din HaGadol. Now, there's an
interesting question about how central their role is, because if you think
about it, what did they do? All they did was they warned
her, right? That's their whole role, to warn her? Big deal. Right?
So far בית דין as well as they've been from one בית
דין to the next בית דין, they're asserting their presence, you know,
but how much are they really doing? Right? They're protecting them from
having sex along the way. They're warning her. Okay. So תוספות Tosafos
has another question. תוספות Tosafos is bothered because he says the chronology
doesn't work, because he says the הלכה of a זקן ממרא Zaken
Mamre is only when the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is situated in the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. We actually know that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin like left
the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. you know, before the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit
because they didn't want to have to deal with responsibility of dealing
with דיני נפשות. dine nefashot. But תוספות Tosafos says the evidence points
to the fact that they were still that they could still be
doing סוטה Sota rituals, you know, at a late at that later
time. So how could that be? It's not fitting this pattern of
the זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos,
let's see what he says. He says,
מה להלן בית דין הגדול, ma lehalan Beit Din HaGadol, תוספות Tosafos
says,
קשיא, kasha, כיון דאלפינן מזקן ממרא, kivan d'alpinan miZaken Mamre, איכא למימר
גבי סוטה שהמקום גורם, ika l'meimar gabei Sota shehamakom gorem, that they
have to be in the in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, כמו גבי זקן ממרא,
k'mo gabei Zaken Mamre, ולכך היו מעלים אותן ללשכת הגזית. ul'kach hayu
ma'alim osan l'Lishkat HaGazit. So אם כן, im ken, if that would
be true, פסקו מים המארים מיום שגלתה סנהדרין pasku mayim hamarim miyom
shegalta Sanhedrin וישבו להם בחנות, v'yashvu lahem b'chanus, כדאמר בפרק הבודק, k'damar
b'Perek HaBodek, the water should have stopped being effective when the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin left the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, And then he proves that
that doesn't seem to work out. So just skip to the bottom
and he says like this, ונראה, v'nira, three lines from the bottom
of the תוספות, Tosafos, דאיום לא היה מעכב. d'iyum lo haya ma'akev.
You know what? The role of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the warning, would
not be מעכב, ma'akev, would not prevent you from going forward. דאם
לא היו מאיימין כלל, d'im lo hayu me'ayimin klal, if they didn't
do this warning and the בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol wasn't
involved in the process, אף על פי כן היתה שותה, af al
pi chen haysa sosa, she could still go through with it. הילכך
היתה נהוגת אפילו אחר הגלות. hilkach haysa nohages afilu achar hagalus. So
the whole thing is almost like exactly paralleling, you know, מן התורה
איש מביא את אשתו. minaTorah ish mevia es ishto. At one level
we like concede you could do without the whole בית דין. Just
go straight to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, You don't need a
בית דין in your ear, you don't need the בית דין to
accompany, you don't need a בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol to
warn. It really is just in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash right?
He's conceding that this איום, iyum, the role of the בית דין
הגדול, Beit Din HaGadol, really was not, if you didn't do it,
it would still work. It was really not a necessary function. So
at the same time we are making it about בית דין and
putting them front and center in the entire process, right? There's a
recognition that technically actually it could all go through without the בית
דין, which by the way answers, and with this point we'll end,
the previous תוספות, Tosafos, I think, and also gets to a question
you were sort of implicitly raising, מה להלן בשבעים ואחד, Ma lehalan
b'shivim v'echad, תוספות Tosafos says, תימא, tema, אמאי לא תני לסוטה וזקן
ממרא, amai lo tani l'Sota v'Zaken Mamre, ולסוטה וזקן ממרא, ul'Sota v'Zaken
Mamre, פרק קמא דסנהדרין Perek Kama d'Sanhedrin בהדי הנך דהוו בבית דין
שבעים ואחד. bahadi hanach d'havay b'Beit Din shivim v'echad. Why don't we
list סוטה Sota and זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre in the cases of
something that needs a בית דין of seventy-one? Okay. ויש אומרים משום
דגמר דסוטה וזקן ממרא לא הוי בבית דין שבעים ואחד. v'yesh omrim
mishum d'gmar d'Sota v'Zaken Mamre lo havay b'Beit Din shivim v'echad. We
wouldn't do the end of the judgment, the end of the סוטה
Sota would be in the בית המקדש, זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre would
go in a different location, but I think it's a question about,
like, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin lists the type of things that require a
בית דין of seventy-one, right?
Some certain, you know, certain types of capital crimes and so on,
need a בית דין of seventy-one. Why doesn't it say סוטה needs
a בית דין of seventy-one? So the real answer is what this
second תוספות Tosafos just told us, because at the end of the
day, she's not being adjudicated in the בית דין and the בית
דין is not really necessary at the end of the day. At
the end of the day, it really is a temple ritual. So
it's quite fascinating you're sort of seeing it at the same time.
It's being the whole thing is being presented as a דין ritual
and then the acknowledgment that really at the end of the day
you could do away with that entire layer and it could exist
as a pure type of a בית המקדש ritual. Okay, we will
end with that today.
Maybe the role of the בית דין is to make it more
for the public, more for more for warning the rest of the
population.
Well, that's what I was saying, that it becomes like a public
ritual like כל העם ישמעו
וייראו.
kol ha'am
yishme'u v'yira'u.
The point purpose is to warn the rest of the population.
Yeah, that's what.